<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-04-19T14:53:22+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">SwadishTa</title><subtitle>Some tech, some non-tech. Some expertise, some exploration.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Never never blog</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/learning/writing/2021/04/18/never-never-blog.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Never never blog" /><published>2021-04-18T11:34:32+05:30</published><updated>2021-04-18T11:34:32+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/learning/writing/2021/04/18/never-never-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/learning/writing/2021/04/18/never-never-blog.html">&lt;p&gt;My earliest thoughts about writing came as inspiration from reading others, of course. I wanted to write down my thoughts as well but did not understand who my &lt;strong&gt;audience&lt;/strong&gt; was. How would I best connect with them? Reaching out to people I read to understand this did not even cross my mind!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though most people I read and liked to read used simple &lt;strong&gt;language&lt;/strong&gt;. I somehow equated using high-sounding words as the basis of an accomplished writer. An oversight that I did not think too deeply about. It was hard to draw a line categorize between the extremes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I would start writing something, there would be constant second-guessing and tinkering, either make the thing sound right or be right or end with the right takeaway. The issue here is I would both &lt;strong&gt;write and edit&lt;/strong&gt; my content at the same time, which made it much much harder to get to the finish line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we come to one of the most cited issues stopping someone. The &lt;strong&gt;imposter syndrome&lt;/strong&gt;, the feeling of not being good enough, being in the wrong place, not having enough depth or breadth of thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could probably add a couple more blockers here! or maybe before the imposter point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I have continued to read others’ articles, listen to them talk about writing, take a short course or two. Over time it seems to me writing is both harder and simpler than I have thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harder, how? Writing, creating something out of thin air, is inherently hard. Heard of some people locking themselves up, Others waiting on the slow drip of inspiration, etc. &lt;strong&gt;Everyone struggles&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then simpler? The simpler part is for us to be conscious about, develop structures and rituals which aid us to get done. To finish is the most critical element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of worrying about the audience, start writing as a personal &lt;strong&gt;journalling&lt;/strong&gt; project. Write about things you are curious about, start observing things around you and bring them to your journal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing helps to develop our observation skills, &lt;strong&gt;clarifying our thoughts&lt;/strong&gt; by forcing a structure on our analyses and conclusions. An early variant of Feynman’s learning method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focus on journalling and our curiosities also enable us to &lt;strong&gt;keep things simple&lt;/strong&gt;, the language, the medium, the scope creep. Simple things can also be taken to the finish in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we then move from a personal journal to a public post? Explicitly share your posts with a few friends and family, and &lt;strong&gt;ask for critical feedback&lt;/strong&gt;. Don’t become defensive to feedback, be curious and engage with the ones who are taking their time out to read you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do this more and more, gradually expand your circle, build up a &lt;strong&gt;learning loop&lt;/strong&gt;, of constant feedback and iteration. This level of engagement is where we usually start seeing the hockey stick curve of personal growth. Not just our writing, but our thought process and mental model of reality will start to transform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final nail to this article is &lt;strong&gt;quantity leads to quality&lt;/strong&gt;. The more you write, the more you will finish, and the better you will write.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Learning" /><category term="Writing" /><summary type="html">My earliest thoughts about writing came as inspiration from reading others, of course. I wanted to write down my thoughts as well but did not understand who my audience was. How would I best connect with them? Reaching out to people I read to understand this did not even cross my mind!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Good fight</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/companies/learning/2020/11/09/the-good-fight.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Good fight" /><published>2020-11-09T16:02:32+05:30</published><updated>2020-11-09T16:02:32+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/companies/learning/2020/11/09/the-good-fight</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/companies/learning/2020/11/09/the-good-fight.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tender-heisenberg-6e14d2.netlify.app/&quot;&gt;Artoo&lt;/a&gt; has shutdown. 6 years of growing up under its influence has added to my value system and life experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been meaning to write about the experiences for a long time but never could get my narrative device straight. Writing about a lived experience with its multi-layered multi-colored linkages is easy to procrastinate about till it melts away in our consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now attempting to unravel this big ball of mud by unspooling threads of gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first came to hear Artoo, the name, through an acquaintance at a health initiative. The website had a young, cheerful presence, and they were looking for Android devs. Professionally I had been about 6 months into android. The interview process was a lot about relatedness to the purpose, belonging to the team, Sameer also brought in the rigor of persistent curiosity. The place felt different in a good way, and i jumped in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some strands which made Artoo for me over these 5+ years,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;empathy&quot;&gt;Empathy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empathy for the borrower, the field agent, our employees, and service providers, and self!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empathy sounds right, but at its core the daily deliberations, decisions and actions. When each interaction and its effects matter, the way we design these interactions changes, as does our way of being and so do we. At Artoo, empathy was a lived value and defined interations inside and outside the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;openness-and-ownership&quot;&gt;Openness and Ownership&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Openness and Autonomy go together, a strand of collaborative decision making is necessary as well. These included off-campus sessions around vision, goals; weekly updates on finances; knowledge sharing sessions; Open office with noisy open meetings. We had our struggles with this, not everything was perfect. If we were to go back i would replace even more ‘but then’s with ‘and’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ownership was not explicitly defined, but an implicit assumption. This was 2 sided knife, people who could work without structure / designations cut though, and others dragged along blunted. We missed a behavioural rubric during hiring which helped long term trillers succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;diversity-and-people&quot;&gt;Diversity and People&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artoo was always had an underlying thread of diversity, in terms of skills, gender, geography. A slight affirmative hint in our hiring policies added to it. We worked with C-Suites, Middle management, IT departments, Field staff; our internal diversity kept us in good stead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interaction at an individual level was encouraged, enabling the gossip protocol to serve our clients better. An Open office with first come first pick seating might have something to do with this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parties, treks, off-road celebrations will always remain enjoyable memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;curiosity-and-drive&quot;&gt;Curiosity and Drive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nous of the team was hacking things together, we started off onboarding field staff to tech-savvy smartphones and crm software; an offline first cloud solution which worked with an occasional crank; a hardware prototype for fingerprint scanner which was passed over. A team of ~15 people for most of our journey, we got things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we grew, our curiosity  re-directed towards productivity and efficiency. We iterated on people systems into our sunset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sameer raged against the tide occasionally, with more show-offs, internal hacks. We should have played more, we got distracted growing up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feedback-and-leverage&quot;&gt;Feedback and Leverage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we grew into adolescence our output did not seem to scale up, we started looking more closely at collaboration and feedback. The team level ones like pods, sprints, agile, then org level OKRs and Balanced Scorecard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cohesive vision and tight feedback-iteration loops provide the leverage small teams need against bigger and better-funded competitors. At our best we used this well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was still scope to enhance effectiveness with a more focused approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-note&quot;&gt;Final note&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inherent opportunities of a small team, making them available across the team and bringing the possibilities to life needs a strong force for good, we had them in Sameer, Kavita and the extended team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-takes-from-colleagues-at-artoo&quot;&gt;Other takes from colleagues at Artoo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kaushikb9/status/1302707444305469440&quot;&gt;Kaushik’s tweet storm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://aparna-52912.medium.com/d1fc4d63feda&quot;&gt;Aparna’s all-encompassing take&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Companies" /><category term="Learning" /><summary type="html">Artoo has shutdown. 6 years of growing up under its influence has added to my value system and life experiences.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On the move</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/companies/learning/2017/04/15/on-the-move.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the move" /><published>2017-04-15T16:02:32+05:30</published><updated>2017-04-15T16:02:32+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/companies/learning/2017/04/15/on-the-move</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/companies/learning/2017/04/15/on-the-move.html">&lt;p&gt;The internet has been abuzz with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sec.gov/Archives/edgar/data/1018724/000119312517120198/d373368dex991.htm&quot;&gt;Jeff’s 2017 letter to shareholders&lt;/a&gt; the last couple of days. It is an impressive, succinct piece with advice about proxies, external trends and customer obsession. I loved it too and read a couple more (older) shareholder letters .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When i think about it now what turned me on was the clarity of people on the move, the achievers and the super achievers amongst us. I doubt they have any fewer doubts than others. The distinction is in moving beyond and being in action while harbouring doubts, while others focus and freeze within those self-doubts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its time to be on the move.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="Companies" /><category term="Learning" /><summary type="html">The internet has been abuzz with Jeff’s 2017 letter to shareholders the last couple of days. It is an impressive, succinct piece with advice about proxies, external trends and customer obsession. I loved it too and read a couple more (older) shareholder letters .</summary></entry></feed>